Inventory of the Harland Bartholomew and Associates Archives, 1961-1974
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Harland Bartholomew and Associates Archives, 1961-1974
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 244
5 linear feet
Harland Bartholomew and Associates Archives
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The materials were donated by the firm to the Special Collections and Archives Department in May 1987.
Biographical/Historical Information
Known as the dean of U.S. city planners, Harland Bartholomew (1889-1989) was considered the greatest authority on municipal planning in the mid-twentieth century. Born in Stoneham, Massachusetts in 1889, Bartholomew became City Planning Commissioner of St. Louis in 1919, the first full-time planner employed by an American city. That year he established Harland Bartholomew and Associates, a city planning consulting firm, serving as its chairman until his retirement in 1962. Bartholomew died December 2, 1989. Harland Bartholomew and Associates continues to be active and has designed city plans for several hundred cities across the United States, including Washington, D.C., and Richmond, Virginia in the Southeast to San Antonio and Los Angeles in the West.
Harland Bartholomew and Associates (HBA) set up several regional offices across the country. An office in Richmond was established in 1961. The Richmond office of HBA began with a focus of providing urban renewal planning services to local governments throughout the East. These services continued to be the primary focus up into the late 1980s and early 1990s. International planning jobs began to become more prevalent in the late 1980s and soon grew to become a major market for the Richmond office in the early 1990s. That led to the establishment of a satellite office in Dubai, United Arab Emirates. The Richmond office also began working for U.S. Department of Defense clients, providing master planning services to military bases around the world as well as supporting similar project being carried out in HBA offices located in St. Louis and Sacramento. By 2002, the Richmond office's main client was the Department of Defense. HBA was purchased by the Parsons Corporation in the late 1980s. Their office in Richmond was designated as Parsons Planning Division.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains federal applications for redevelopment loans and grants, project reports and plans, and published reports on various areas of Richmond.
Arrangement
The collection has no particular order, but is housed in the scrapbook area.
Contents List
- Randolph Urban Renewal Project 1972 (Box 1)
- Survey and Planning Application for Downtown Redevelopment Project 1961 (Box 2)
- 17th Street Redevelopment Project 1965 (Box 2)
- RRHA, Application for Community Renewal Grant 1966 (Box 2)
- RRHA, Amedatory Application for Loan and Grant for the 17th Street Redevopment Project 1965 (Box 2)
- RRHA, Downtown Redevelopment Project (Box 2)
- Community Renewal Program 1966 (Box 2)
- Petersburg Redevelopment and Housing Authority 1969 (Box 3)
- Hopewell Redevelopment and Housing Authority 1969 (Box 4)
- Washington Park, Fulton, George Mason, Jefferson Park Neighborhood Program 1975 (Box 4)
- Washington Park Conservation Project 1966 (Box 5)
- Gillfield Project, Petersburg 1972 (Box 5)
- Downtown Project, Richmond 1961 (Box 5)
- Gillfield Urban Renewal, Petersburg 1969 (Box 6)
- Washington Park and Fulton, Neighborhood Redevelopment 1971 (Box 6)
- Hopewell Redevelopment 1973 (Box 7)
- Fulton Neighborhood Renewal 1966 (Box 7)
- Shockoe Valley Flood Disaster Area 1972 (Box 8)
- Hopewell Renewal Project 1971 (Box 8)
- Washington Park, Fulton, George Mason, Jefferson Park Neighborhood Program 1972 (Box 8)
- 17th Street Renewal Project, Richmond 1964 (Box 8)